ע"ט, Ayin Tet, 79, and we pick up on the bottom of
ע"ח עמוד ב', Ayin Chet amud bet,
and we pick up with the two dots where it says three
lines from the bottom, and we had just introduced the position of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, that the husband is entitled to the
פירות perot from the wife's property that she brings into the marriage,
and then we saw a whole series of debates about how much
we would entitle him to also stop the sale of those properties,
clearly that would only be a possibility once there was נישואין nissuin
not אירוסין, erusin, that he could block the sale. But once there
was נישואין, nissuin, if the property, and if the property came after
the נישואין, nissuin, then he could. And then there was a whole
debate about once the property came before the נישואין, nissuin, now there's
נישואין, nissuin, can he block the sale of his wife's properties? Okay,
but basically he gets the פירות perot and in some circumstances he
didn't even block the sale of it. And then we have רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who distinguishes in terms of, not just in terms
of the entitlement to פירות, perot, but in terms of when he
can block the sale. He can block the sale on property that
he was aware of, not that he wasn't aware of, properties that
were overseas. How exactly we measure overseas is not clear. רש"י Rashi
explains that the basis of the difference is that he can't say
that he was anticipating those properties, and so therefore those are ones,
at least certainly if they're ones that came from before the marriage,
it sounds like he's not entitled to block their sale. Okay, so
now we pick up with that in mind, the next סוגיא, sugya,
which we're going to see will tie in and deal with the
nuances of the fact that a woman has property and what type
of legal devices she might be able to use to protect it
given that the husband now has been given these rights. So we
pick up three lines from the bottom with a case story: ההיא
איתתא דבעיא דתבריכינהו לנכסה מגברה, Hahi itta de-ba'ya d'tavrichinah l'nichseh mi-gavrah,
she wanted to hide her property away, really like a
case-of-moss from her husband. Okay, so she, רש"י Rashi gives a little
bit more background details to the רש"י Rashi first of all at
the line at the bottom: אלמנה הות, Almanah havata, she was a
widow, ובעיא דתינסב, u'ba'ya d'tinasav, and she wanted to marry, ואתיא מקדמת
ונתנה לברתה, v'asya mikademas v'nasna l'bitah,
this is why רש"י Rashi says she's a widow because then we
see she had a daughter, כדי לאברוחי זכות בעל מהם, kedei l'avruchey
zechus ba'al meihem, שלא יזכה בהם. shelo yizkeh bahem.
Okay, so basically, you know, it's writing over your property in the
name of your spouse in order to protect it from the creditors,
so we know that phenomenon. So this is a case of writing
over her property into her daughter's, giving it to her daughter to
protect it from her husband. So it's not her property then besides
the issue about her being able to sell it, which had been
the focus of our משנה, mishna, once she gets married there's the
things that underpins it with the husband's rights to the פירות. perot.
So let's say she wants to not have the husband have the
right to those פירות, perot, what can she do? Protect her property
to start, to stop her husband from getting all of the income
from all of the property that she has. So one is she
might want to have an explicit stipulation with the husband, and when
you get then a later, in a later
משנה, mishna, in a later פרק perek about a woman who basically
makes has her husband stipulate with her to withdraw his rights from
her property. But this was not exactly that type of a marriage,
whatever it was, that wasn't going to happen. So what she opted
to, what she did was she wrote it over into her daughter's
name and therefore the husband would not have the פירות, perot, the
right, any of the rights in property. So back to the גמרא:
Gemara: ההיא איתתא דבעיא דתבריכינהו לנכסה מגברה, Hahi itta de-ba'ya d'tavrichinah l'nichseh
mi-gavrah, she wanted to case away her property from her husband, כתבתינהו
לברתה, kasvasinhu l'bitah,
she wrote it over in her daughter's name. This was before she
got married because if it was after she got married then the
husband could block the sale possibly, right? So she wrote it over
to her daughter's name. אינסבא, isvei, she got married to the guy,
ואיגרשה, v'idrashah, and then she got divorced, and that's why you have
point up to Le-Olam because sometimes they get in a divorce, okay,
so she takes her life, fine, no problem. אתאי לקמיה דרב נחמן,
asya l'kamei d'Rav Nachman, she came in front of רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman.
So now what happened that's missing from the story is, okay, you'd
say שמע ישראל, Shema Yisrael, she gets her daughter back, her property
back from her daughter, but her daughter now said, "Thanks for the
property, Mom." So,
and her daughter doesn't want to give it back to the mother.
And the only reason this would become an issue after the גירושין
gerushin because during the גירושין gerushin she can't ask for the property
back unless she have a side arrangement with her daughter that the
daughter gives her the income from the property, wonderful, but she can't
actually after you know, ask for the property back while she's married
because she needs to keep it in her daughter's name. But now
that she's divorced again, she wants to take that property back and
the daughter doesn't want to give it and she says, "Look, you
you signed it over to me." So אתאי לקמיה דרב נחמן, asya
l'kamei d'Rav Nachman, came in front of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, קרעיה
רב נחמן לשטרא, kara Rav Nachman l'shetara, רב נחמן Rav Nachman ripped
up the document, the gift document to the daughter. He's like, "Yeah,
this whole thing was just a ruse to keep it away from
the
husband," so. the husband? You can't have it both. Now by the
way also רש"י Rashi says that there were explicit witnesses that the
women had sort of presented to before she gave it over to
the daughter that I want you to know that I'm giving this
over to my daughter but it's only like on paper this isn't
real, etc. and she had actual witnesses to testify that it wasn't
a real gift. תוספות Tosafot says that doesn't sound like it from
the גמרא, Gemara, people were about to challenge רב נחמן Rav Nachman
as we're about to see, so it does not sound like there
were witnesses. It just sounds like רב נחמן Rav Nachman made that
judgment call based on the context. The context was clear enough and
obvious enough that even without witnesses and even though the daughter had
a שטרא, shtara, that was enough for him to say it was
not good, which is quite amazing. That the daughter has a שטרא
shtara and just looking at enough of the circumstantial evidence was enough
for רב נחמן Rav Nachman to say yes, but you didn't really
want to give it to your daughter and he tore up this
שטרא. shtara. So, basically, yeah, in an...
when the marriage is over, when the pretense is over it goes
back or the guy comes in and he wants more crackers? Forget
it.
Right, exactly. So if
we take a look at the
last תוספות Tosafot on ע"ט Ayin Tet עמוד ב', Amud Bet, תוספות
Tosafot says ונראה דאף על גב דלא מסרה מודעא לשום עדים, v'nireh
d'af al gav d'lo masrah moda'ah l'shum edim, דממילא הוא ניכר, d'mimaila
hu nikar, ולא היו דברים שבלב, v'lo hayu devarim shebalev, and it
wasn't like anything you didn't say explicitly doesn't count, שאין דברים שבלב,
she'ein devarim shebalev, והכא ניכר הדבר שהוא לא נתכוונה אלא להבריח, v'hacha
nikar hadavar shehu lo nitkavnah ela lehavriach, it was evident, it was
clear that that was
her only intention, דנפשה עדיפא לה מהא דברתה ושבקה לה להאי מתנה
לנפשה, d'nafshah adifa lah me'ha d'bartah v'shavkah lah le'hai matanah lenafshah, and
I have to remind you that according to רמב"ן Ramban and the
תוספות הראש, Tosafot ha'Rosh, the idea of דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim
shebalev einam devarim is a much bigger problem in a two-sided transaction
because the person could say if I'm paying for it you can't
have some secret intent in mind. But in a one-sided transaction like
a gift, then much more we try to assess what was the
state of mind of the person giving the gift. So רב נחמן
Rav Nachman tore up the document, tore it up, and of course
then the question is going to be how did it work to
keep it away from the husband? Let's see where the story goes.
אזל רב ענן לקמיה דמר עוקבא, Azal Rav Anan lekamei d'Mar Ukva,
so רב ענן Rav Anan saw this and he went to מר
עוקבא Mar Ukva to complain. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, חזי מר נחמן חקלאה היכי מקרע שטרי דאינשי, Chazi Mar Nachman
Chakla'ah heichi makra shtarei d'inshei, did you see רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
the Mr. נחמן, Nachman, the farmer, how he tears up the documents
of people? Meaning he is dispensing them like he is not even
like a דיין, dayan, he is supposed to be a farmer or
something.
Okay, tearing up people's documents. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, איני איזי גופא דעובדא היכי הוה, Eini izi gufa d'uvda heichi
hava, tell me, is like an idiom, tell me in truth,
tell me the whole story, let me hear what רב נחמן... Rav
Nachman... let me hear what really went down. Let me hear the
whole story like instead of all about רב נחמן Rav Nachman tearing
up the שטרא, shtara, let me hear the whole story. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, he said to him, הכי והכי הוה. Hachi v'hachi hava.
Look, this is what happened, listen. And he told him this and
he told him that, he told him the whole story. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so then מר עוקבא Mar Ukva said back, שטרא מברחת
קאמרת? Shtara mavrachat ka'amrat?
You're talking about a document that is done for hide... for like
chasing away the property? Right, there was even a name for
it. שטרא מברחת, Shtara mavrachat, right. Right, a document to run away,
to chase away the property, to hide the property. הכי אמר רב
חנילאי אמר שמואל, Hachi amar Rav Chanilai amar Shmuel, so this is
what רב חנילאי Rav Chanilai said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel,
מורה הוראה אני, Moreh hora'ah ani, I am a מורה הוראה, moreh
hora'ah, I am a פוסק, posek, I have authority from the ריש
גלותא, Reish Galuta, יורה יורה, yoreh yoreh, which means as רש"י Rashi
says, נטלה רשות
מריש גלותא, natlah reshut me'Reish Galuta, like this whole idea of יורה
יורה yoreh yoreh that they have not just הוראה, hora'ah, it was
the רבי Rebbe allowing the תלמיד, talmid, acknowledging the תלמיד's talmid's knowledge
and allowing the תלמיד talmid to פסקן pasken in his presence, but
it was also that they had authority from the government to פסקן
pasken which had certain other implications. So this is sort of in
contrast to saying oh, he's just a farmer. So look, what did
he say about רב נחמן? Rav Nachman? מורה הוראה אני, Moreh hora'ah
ani, I am a פוסק, posek, I have authority from the ריש
גלותא, Reish Galuta, I know what I'm talking about, and what did
I say? אי יבא שטרא מברחת
לידי, Ei yava shtara mavrachat l'yadi, if I ever get presented with
one of these chasing away שטראות, shtarot, one of these secret-it-away-the-property שטראות,
shtarot, אקרענו, ekra'enu, I tear it up as well. Okay, and presumably
also, how do you know it's a שטרא מברחת? shtara mavrachat? Presumably
you'd be able to look at the circumstances. So if this is
a phenomenon and they're allowed to look at the circumstances and make
that judgment call. אמר רבא לרב נחמן, Amar Rava l'Rav Nachman, so
רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, טעמא מאי? Ta'ama mai?
One minute,
he said, look, what is the reason for why רב נחמן Rav
Nachman tore up the document? רבא Rava said to him, what's the
reason that you're tearing it up and you're assuming it wasn't a
real gift? טעמא מאי? Ta'ama mai? דלא שביק איניש נפשיה ויהיב לאחריני,
d'lo shavik inish nafshiah v'yahiv l'achrinei,
so presumably the normal reason you'd tear up a שטרא מברחת shtara
mavrachat as שמואל Shmuel said that he would do it, is because
you would
not like abandon yourself and give your property to some others. third
party. Like why would you סתם, stam, you know, it’s one thing
on a deathbed request or whatever, but סתם stam to give away
all of your property to a third party? That at least is
a very suspicious circumstance as a straight gift, and that entitles us
to assume that this was really meant as a farce and it
wasn't sincere. Okay, that’s the normal argument. But this isn’t a stranger.
אמאי, amai, that’s not just a third party, it’s a ברתא barta
or בר bar too, but people sometimes do give over their property
to their children even while they’re alive, even if they’re not on
their deathbed. So maybe you don’t have the same type of circumstantial
evidence that it wasn't sincere. So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו הכי
במקום ברתא נפשיה עדיפא afilu hachi bimkom barta nafshai adifa and the
response is no, even so, במקום ברתא נפשיה עדיפא. bimkom barta nafshai
adifa. When it's you know compared to your daughter, not just daughter,
your son, your whatever, you know, you know, your self comes first.
You know, it's like חייך וחיי דסמיכי חייך קודמין. chayecha v'chaye d'samchi
chayecha kodmin.
Even if it's family, you don’t סתם stam give away all of
your property. Look, just
read or whatever Shakespeare King Lear, you understand what happens if you
give all your property to your kids and expect them to take
care of you. Shakespeare, I understand, so anyway all right. So it
gets so, you might give some gift, but I mean you might
have them in your will and you might do different things, but
you won't סתם stam right away all your property to your kids
or any third party. So that sets the question, right, like what
if it’s some of the property, not all the property, how do
you look at those circumstantial things to make that judgment call? Yes.
She made it a conditional gift in order to work this out,
the mother to the daughter?
That’s a חמש chomesh
sort of
thing.
Yeah, that's an interesting question, like why didn't she just sort of
make it conditional, right? Why didn't she sort of say like, it's
all sold to me but in the possibility that I eventually, but
no because then it would, if I get divorced then it was
never sold, then retroactively the husband would say, okay, so retroactively it
was never sold, so now for the divorce, so now give me
back payment for the last 10 years.
Why did it
have to be at that
moment? You can פטר מן השלוח? patar min hashiluach?
Yeah, that's what נחום Nachum essentially.
I understand, I understand.
That’s what he said.
No, because look, I guess the interesting question, who's entitled to the
income during the last 10 years? Your son? Right. No, if it’s
the daughter she gave it to her, she’s entitled to the income.
In this case, let's say the whole thing was a farce, give
me back the property. But Rashi says, so but the husband
wouldn't be entitled.
What? Well, if it was never a sale, there’s two possibilities. If
it was, right, if it was never a sale then how does
the question, if it was never a sale then how does it
work at all? Okay, סוגיא. sugya. I guess your point about making
it a תנאי t'nai is no different than the whole thing was
a farce and we still have to deal with why the husband
doesn't get it for the interim.
Right. Right, exactly for the interim, right. And the daughter? Right,
the mother can't give... All right, so let's see what the... So
you could be, yeah, it could be an explicit תנאי. t'nai. Look,
the bottom line we're going to have to figure out, if it
was never, if it was a good sale, how does the mother
get it back? And if it was never a good sale, how
did she keep it away from the husband? So let's take a
look. Well, let's just get to the end and then get back
to questions. Okay, so it says like this, it says, okay, מתיב
metiv asks on this. So what's this? הרוצה שתבריח נכסיה מבעלה. Harotzah
shetavriach nechasia miba'alah. That’s the תוספתא. Tosefta. Somebody who wants to, it's
so funny, right, you know right after talking about the husband's rights
and then בשמעוני be-Shimoni where we're embarrassed that we gave the husband
so much rights to block the sale, the תוספתא Tosefta and the
גמרא Gemara basically layout ways to give the woman a workaround to
this. So wait a minute. הרוצה שתבריח נכסיה מבעלה. Harotzah shetavriach nechasia
miba'alah. A woman wants to transfer away her property from her husband.
כיצד היא עושה? Keitzad hi osah? What can she do? כותבת שטר
פסים לאחרים. Kotevet shtar pasim l'acherim.
She writes a fake document to other people.
דברי שמעון בן מנסיא. Divrei Shimon ben Menasya. That's what שמעון בן
מנסיא Shimon ben Menasya says. So רש"י Rashi says
as כותבת שטר פסים. Kotevet shtar pasim. And רש"י Rashi says here
the word פסים pasim means פיוסים שמפייסת אותו לקבל מתנה זו. piyusim
shemefayeset oto lekabel matanah zo. רש"י Rashi says it says like I
don't know, a... no,
yeah, whatever, I don't know an enticement, an enticement document, a persuasion,
I don't know what, it's hard to translate. It basically means, it
basically means like a fake document to others. That's what שמעון בן
מנסיא Shimon ben Menasya says. וחכמים אומרים רצה משחק בה עד
שתכתוב
לו מהיום ולכשארצה.
V'chachamim omrim ratza mesachek bah ad
shetichtov lo mehayom u'lechisheerze. Now, that the one who receives the gift
can laugh in her face, thank you very much, and I’m walking
away. So this is basically the debate we saw before with רב
נחמן Rav Nachman and הני רבוותא. hani rabvata. You write a document
to other people, they get it. If she wants to protect it,
it’s not enough to say, oh you know make it look real
but say that it’s fake. But you have to make it really,
you have to concretely do something to limit the other person’s control.
So what do you do? So it says עד שתכתוב לו מהיום
ולכשארצה. ad shetichtov lo mehayom u'lechisheerze. And
that’s what you were saying David. You have to have an explicit
condition. This property belongs to you, and but I maintain the power
at any time to reverse the gift. Okay. Okay, so and then
it seems though like David, and then it seems though no, but
that would seem though,
well
it's an interesting idea that you have the right to reverse it,
but it seems though that once she does choose to exercise that
right, it's like she's owned it in fact for the last 10
years, right, so then becomes the person who gets that income for
the last 10 years. So if you look at Rashi says, עד
שתכתוב, Ad shetichtov, it's quite, Rashi's on the side of the husband
here. בשטרי זה מהיום יסומכה וכשארצה יש כאן הזנחה מפורשת. Bishtarei zeh
mehayom yesumacha ucheshertzeh yesh kan hazvacha mefurash. That is the point. Tomorrow
I want to take back the
gift. If the husband wants to get the property she says, "No,
I want it to be a gift." פניתי למי שמסייע. Paniti lemi
she-mesayea. וזה שכתב בשעה ובזמן שיאמר איני רוצה. V'zeh she-chasav b'shaa u-vizman
she-yomar eini rotzeh.
Okay,
so it's not clear also according to Rashi that even if she
says איני רוצה eini rotzeh retroactively there's never a gift, right, or
is it that it's just from now and on?
Because of course what this guy could always do is if he
could go into collusion with the husband and say, "Look, let's just
you know, I'll give you my power of attorney and let the
husband come and say, 'Look, it's either your property, you the wife,
so I'm entitled to the fruit, or this guy's property and he
gave me his power of attorney, right, so and I'm going to
collect fruits and then we can split it.'" So anyway, yeah, we
get that.
Historically,
things like like soft commitment and admission and היתר עסקא heter iska
and פרוזבול, prosbol, did they exist at this time or not?
No. A פרוזבול prosbol was. Not soft commitment. Right.
But this is, the problem is with those things like היתר עסקא
heter iska or פרוזבול prosbol is בין אדם לחברו, bein adam l'chavero,
but anyway, but this is real, this is a real, this is
right, this is more getting out of, you know, somebody else's, you
know, somebody else's interest that covers one person at the expense of
another. So anyway, so this is what it is, so it sounds
like כנכסים שאינם ידועים kenichasim she-einam yeduyim just the context is, and
the חכמים Chachamim explicitly, it's not clear according to the חכמים Chachamim
and according to the תנאי, t'nai, does that mean that retroactively it
was never binding, or does that just mean that it's not binding
מכאן ולהבא. mikan u-l'haba. What exactly is the story? Let's anyway take
a look, I want to read the and talk about the mechanism
that operates here. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says
like this: טעמא דכתב ליה הכי. Taama d-chasav lei hachi. So the
reason is, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, if it was written. הא
לא כתב ליה הכי קנייה לוקח. Ha lo chasav lei hachi kanyei
lo-keach. If it wasn't written, then the purchaser gets it. So and
that seems to be again, right, it seems that the חכמים Chachamim
argue on רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. רב נחמן Rav Nachman is just
calling the thing a דמיון. dimyon. So now I'm getting to Michael's
point. אמר רבא לא קשיא הא בכולה הא במקצתה. Amar Rava lo
kashya ha b'kula ha b'miktzata. It depends whether it's all the property.
To שמואל Shmuel and רב נחמן Rav Nachman says you don't need
it to be written explicitly, that's all the property. Then it's clear
that that was only a, you know, that was only a farce,
that was a fake. אנן סהדי, anan sahadi, right, אנן סהדי, anan
sahadi, right, לא שביק איניש. lo shavik inish. But
on part of the property, you need something more explicit.
And now the גמרא
Gemara
says like this: ואי לא כתב ליה קנייה לוקח, V'ee lo chasav
lei kanyei lo-keach, finally the גמרא Gemara asks, "Okay, but if the
whole thing was a farce, whatever the reason is, it was explicit
or it was implicit, so he doesn't own it, וליקנייה בעל, v'likniyah
baal, וכי שתקי אנן סהדי, v'chi shatki anan sahadi, ומזידא חזו אנן
סהדי, u-mizida chazu anan sahadi, you don't have it both ways." So
the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר אביי עשאום כנכסים שאינם ידועים לבעל
ואליבא דרבי שמעון. Amar Abaye asu-un k'nichasim she-ein yeduyim l'baal v'aliba d'Rabbi
Shimon. Ah, this relies on רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says that if the husband doesn't know of the property, he's
not entitled to it, and this makes it sound like, not entitled
to the פירות, peiros, right? We thought in the משנה mishna that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was only talking about the right to block
the sale, but this whole point of this is to block the
husband from the פירות, peiros, okay? And therefore it says, but if
he doesn't know about it, he's not entitled to it, and having
this thing that makes it like she doesn't own it, even though
it's a farce, or whatever it becomes, clearly we know it's a
farce, but that on paper it's not hers, is like אין ידועים,
ein yeduyim, it's another declaration that you don't have rights to these,
you don't have a right to expect this, which is quite fascinating,
right, which means that at the same time the rabbis basically gave
the husband all of these rights to the פירות, peiros, etc. Okay,
and you couldn't, she could always negotiate it with her husband, but
a woman isn't always in that position financially and for other reasons
to make those, you know, in that position of power to negotiate
that and to get the husband to agree not to accept the
פירות. peiros. So they basically at the same time they gave him
those rights, they gave her a vehicle to avoid them, right? If
you basically not only say this thing she's bought away with, but
things you could make it as if he's not aware of it,
they're hidden from the husband,
hidden from אין ידועים, ein yeduyim, or hidden, no, it doesn't matter,
on paper it looks like somebody else owns it, we will give
you this basically this tax shelter, which is all a fake, but
if you go through this procedure it protects it, it shelters it
from the husband. And then she can do what
unilaterally, she won't? Because the whole thing doesn't work, she doesn't own
it, right? No, she will, she's trying to get it back after
she gets divorced, she's entitled to it, it never was a sale,
so the person then would have to give it back.
If she gets divorced she gets it back anyway,
right.
It sounds from the end of the story of the גמרא Gemara
that that the sale was never binding at all, but the fact
that on paper you put it in the שטר shtar was enough
to protect it from the husband. But it was never binding, and
she's entitled to all of the income over that period. That seems
to be clear.
Yes, as a daughter of her previous marriage? Yes. I mean, this
is a rather sophisticated kind of decision, rather than the normal kind
of.
Right, right, and also you have to run with it, yes, right,
because often those cases of the young woman or whatever doesn't have
property going in. Right, but it could apply to a case of
the first marriage.
Yes, in which she used?
She could do it to a third party, it seems.
Anybody, right.
Or below her option? I mean, a woman, she's arranging for her
dowry.
No, so let me, so let me back you off of this,
I want to reiterate this. What's optional, the dowry, is the נכסי
צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. It's the amount that the father agrees
and that then gets over entitled to the husband. Now, even there
there might be certain social pressures or whatever that you'd rather not
give a certain amount over, but you feel pressure to give it
over. You might remember. It's a negotiation. Right, right, you might remember
that there was a story where somebody slapped over alongside somebody else
and embarrassed somebody to write over the. But that's the נדוניא, nedunya,
that really is, you know, optional. But
נכסי מלוג nichsei milog are not optional. נכסי מלוג nichsei milog are
any property in the wife's name, the husband's entitled to the פירות.
peirot.
Exactly, exactly, the property with which she enters the marriage. No. No.
Or is she taking some property and making putting it. She's just
making a decision that I don't need to make myself more attractive
by being wealthier. I can protect this for my.
Yeah, but you're making it sound, that's not conceptually the way it
is. You're making it sound like she's choosing to bring, she's choosing
to take it away, but in a normal case she's choosing to
give the husband the rights to this property. She's not choosing anything.
She's choosing not to give.
Right, so that's what we've done. We've basically said that the husband
has total rights to the income from her property. Now she wants,
you know, it started off with that idea. It's not like she's
choosing to bring it in. Whatever property she happens to have, if
her husband ran with high accountants and do an audit, he'd be
entitled to it because he has rights to the פירות peirot of
her property. So at the same time we're giving him all those
rights without her choosing to give them anything or giving her the
option of choosing to take it away from him. Right, okay, then
that's what I'm saying, that's what's very powerful here, is that we
did do this device that protected her, that allowed her to take
it away. Now, I want to read to you a practical thing,
let me just read תוספות עשוין. Tosafos asuyin. It says like this.
It
says וכבר גמר מעשה, vechvar gamar ma'aseh, okay, and the line starts
here מעשה, ma'aseh, it's about ten lines before the תוספות Tosafos דיבור
המתחיל. dibur hamatchil. תוספות Tosafos מעשה. ma'aseh. Okay, it says וכבר גמר
מעשה שבא מבריח נכסיו לפני רבינו תם. vechvar gamar ma'aseh sheba mavriach
nechasav lifnei Rabbeinu Tam. So let's say you vote. Now here is
somebody who wanted to use this device not in the case of
a husband and a wife, but in the case of I want
to borrow a million dollars, and I wanted to protect my property
from having any liens on it. So I'm going to do the
same type of a thing, I'm going to put fake away my
property before I borrow the million dollars from you. So שלשה עורבות,
shelosha orvot, it says שלשה עורבות ולא רצה שישתעבדו נכסיו לבעל חובו,
shelosha orvot velo ratza sheyishtabdu nechasav leba'al chovo, וגם שבא מבריח נכסיו,
vegam sheba mavriach nechasav, שלא ישתעבדו נכסיו לכתובת אשתו. shelo yishtabdu nechasav
lictuvat ishto. And there's also a case of מבריח נכסיו mavriach nechasav
where I don't want my wife also, she's also potentially a creditor
because she has a lien on my property. So before I got
married and before I borrowed a million dollars, I wrote away my
property to somebody else. Okay? Exactly,
exactly. I tried to put it away. I tried to shelter it.
Okay.
ואמר רבינו תם, ve'amar Rabbeinu Tam, ששטר קיים ומחויב בדבר, sheshtar kayam
umichuyav badavar, that you know what? The person that I gave it
to, he owns now all the property, it wasn't a שטר מברחת,
shtar mavrachet, it was a real שטר. shtar. Why? דדוקא הכא דהוי
מברחת לא קני בעל. dedavka hacha dehavei mavrachet lo kani ba'al. The
only time we're going to allow
שטר מברחת shtar mavrachet is in this case that that can work,
that could be a fake שטר shtar work. How can it be
a fake שטר shtar work? דהוו נכסים שאינן ידועים, dehavu nechasim she'einan
yeduyim, אמינא דבמבריח נתכוון. aminei debemavriach nitkavein.
Here the mechanism is it's possible for me to own property and
my husband not have rights to it. What is it? It's property
that's not known to my husband. So we've got this category of
property that I own that he doesn't have rights, so if I
do something to basically make it officially as if it's not known,
then I can still own it and he wouldn't have rights. And
that's what we say happens when I write the שטר מברחת. shtar
mavrachet. אבל בשאר עורבין, aval bish'ar oirvin, in a normal case, if
I'm if I'm borrowing money, there's no way I can stop you
from having rights unless it's genuinely not my property. Got that? So
therefore he
says אבל במעשים אלו אי לא הוי קני לוקח הוי קני ליה
לבעל חובו ולאשה. aval b'ma'asim eilu i lo havei kani loke'ach havei
kani lei leba'al chovo ule'isha. In this case, there's no category that
if you can own it without your creditors having
rights, so דאישתעבדו בהכי לא הוי מבריח, de'ishtabdu behachi lo havei mavriach,
and since you would not really. from your creditors or your wife
without doing a genuine transfer of ownership, so
then let's say go down to the
business school counts, quote-unquote, because he's got a... and you've got to
understand the logic. You've got a שטר, shtar, there's no legitimate legal
mechanism the שטר shtar would operate in so other than being genuine,
so therefore we're gonna say it's genuine. Okay, I don't know, so
at my בית דין beit din I might have said that that
sounds like a type of
like a מיגו, migo, you know, it's a גו מילתא gu milta
that he wasn't really intending to do it. Okay, but nevertheless there
you see that this idea of מברחת mivrachat generally does not work.
There's no way to protect the property. Either you really give it
away, or have a lien. The only way is by this case
of אישה isha according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who allowed her
to own property but it could be officially not recognized, you know,
not accessible by the husband. So again, quite powerful that at the
same time we give the husband all these rights, you have this
שטר מברחת shtar mivrachat and then you have this device that basically
allows a woman to always to keep all of her property away
from her husband.
Yes. Couple of things. I thought we don't פסקן pasken like רבי
שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon?
Right, that is correct. So תוספות Tosafot says, so תוספות Tosafot has
two opinions, right? One opinion is
that we don't פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon but we
use his logic for this one case. According to that, that's even
a stronger statement. It means that there's really no legal logical device
here, but we still want to give the woman the opportunity to
protect her property. And the other thing is no, that חכמים Chachamim
decided that the פסק psak like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Either way,
okay, it's a powerful statement about taking the position, you know, to
allow the woman this protection.
The other thing is I thought that in a marriage, you know,
we do want the women to have means, so in case of
a divorce or becoming a widow, she would and and that now
that doesn't have any...
Yeah, you don't make policy decisions each time. Policy determines the law
but when you actually have the court case, you judge by the
law.
And then I think of a very very contemporary example of these
things. You know, there're a lot of lawsuits, especially in the financial
crisis, against these executives and whatever. You know, so what a lot
of them did is they would sell properties outright to their wives.
Exactly. I
know,
what happens all the time. But then
what's the consequences? That other person really does own it. And if
that wife divorces her husband, turns around and divorces her husband, she
walks away with all the property. So that nobody denies that you
genuinely can do this. The question is, can you have your cake
and eat it too, right? Can you do it and
still and still retain ownership? And that's the answer. Yes, she's allowed
for this type of a fake and that by the way goes
back to the point that even though, you know, sometimes it might
require an explicit תנאי tenai or whatever, it doesn't seem that you
ever really need it to be owned by the other person in
the interim. Even if you sort of say retroactively, 'I'm going to
exercise my right,' and retroactively you never owned it, it doesn't then
say the husband can't come and say give me my פירות peirot
because nevertheless the existence of such a שטר shtar is enough to
basically say this is shielded, I think that was the word I
was looking for, shielded from the husband. Yes.
Can I take it a step further? The woman had property and
she decided to gift it to someone in her property. What would
happen if this happened here? She has this property then she divorces,
would she also get her כתובה? ketubah?
Sure. Yeah. Because it's not like because it's not like, I mean,
you're right, you know, there're cases where women are the wife or
the husband are not living up to their obligations and then they
lose כתובה ketubah or we force a divorce or so on. She's
not not living up to her obligations. She just protected her property
before the marriage. If she had the property and didn't hand over
the פירות, peirot, she wouldn't be living up to her obligations. But
here she just used the legal devices at her disposal to make
it
that the property was not eligible, was not, you know, for the
husband's rights.
Something like this is standard practice. Exactly. Conscious of what this thing
is all about, protects the woman.
Yeah, I mean, that's what's so fascinating. Right, is that we give
all these types of other devices and all these ways of... I
mean, it really does show how חז"ל Chazal understood the complexity of,
you know, of relationships and of marriages, right? You and and the
woman could say, right, you know, what's... the husband might be able
to say, הרי מעשה ידיך במזונותייך, harei ma'aseh yadayich b'mezonotayich, she could
say, איני ניזונת ואיני עושה, eini nizonet v'eini osah, right? There's all
these different ways...
And also if she made a תנאי, tenai, right, as we said.
Yeah, she could stipulate, but that requires the husband to agree. This
is so much easier, she just does it unilaterally. Okay, one more
question, then we gotta move on. Sorry. Go ahead.
Michael's point is interesting. That rule against selling it to your wife
would not have worked in community property states like California. Right, I
was thinking... but the interesting thing is this this seems to be
siding not with community property type
of...
Does it say whether the husband's aware of this arrangement?
No, I mean,
it does no,
I mean, it
doesn't no, he doesn't need to be aware. I mean, if he
comes to try to collect, he'll become aware, but no. The whole
point is that it seems to be unilateral. Okay, let's look at
this next משנה mishnah. *Mishna*. נכסים שנפלו לה עד שלא תתארס *Nechasim
she’naflu lah ad shelo tita’res*. Now, who gets the פירות peirot, *peirot*
of her property? Now, I've been saying פירות peirot *peirot*, I've been
trying to abstract it and talk about income. But what if the
משנה mishnah *Mishna* now, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now is going to
deal with, what if it's stuff that is not real fields? How
do you convert it? And what's it going to... does the husband
have a right to insist that it be converted? How do you
convert it to a type of an income-generating thing, to fields with
פירות peirot *peirot*? Okay, and does it always have to be fields
and פירות peirot *peirot*, or could there be other types of income-generating
things that you don't... the קרן keren? *keren* remains, right? הקרן קיימת
לו לעולם הבא והפירות שהוא אוכל בעולם הזה *Ha-keren kayemet lo la-olam
ha-ba ve-ha-peirot she-hu ochel ba-olam ha-zeh*. So קרן keren? *keren* generates the...
you want to make sure that you don't... you maintain the principal
and that it generates the income for the husband. So let's take
an example. נפלו לה כספים *Nafal lah kesafim*. So
she got an inheritance of money. She has a million dollars in
the bank, okay? And it was in a non-interest-bearing account or whatever.
They didn't really have that then. So what are you going to
do? ילקח בהן קרקע והוא אוכל פירות yilakach bahen karka vehu ochel
peirot. *Yilkach bahen karka ve-hu ochel peirot*. They buy fields and he
eats the fruits. Yeah, it sounds like the husband is entitled to
insist that it gets converted into something that is that produces income
and specifically קרקע karka, *karka* with פירות peirot, *peirot*. פירות peirot. התלושים
מן הקרקע *Peirot ha-tlushim min ha-karka*. What if she gets fruit, you
know? She inherited she inherited like a granary with all this, you
know, cut wheat or whatever. ילקח בהן קרקע karka והוא אוכל פירות
peirot. *Yilkach bahen karka ve-hu ochel peirot*. Same story, buy the fields
which then generate פירות peirot *peirot*. Now, what if it's פירות המחוברים
לקרקע peirot hamichubarim lakarka, *Peirot ha-mechubarim la-karka*? Let's say she inherited fruits
that are attached to the field, and presumably it sounds like it's
together with this... yeah, I see on the trees. Presumably with the
trees themselves, okay? So then... no, presumably I'm sorry, presumably with the
land. Well, we'll see. Okay. So in that case, do you basically
say that that's like land? It sounds like it is with the
land. Okay, we're going to... I'm going to assume that. Or do
you think that that's not land? So let's see. We'll see those
two examples. אמר רבי מאיר *Amar Rabbi Meir*, שמין אותן כמה היא
יפה עם פירות peirot וכמה היא יפה בלא פירות peirot, *Shamim otam
kamah hi yafah im peirot ve-kamah hi yafah belo peirot*. You figure
out how much is this property worth before the trees have all
the oranges on them and how much is it worth now that
the trees have the oranges? So you figure out how much is
the value of the oranges that are on the
trees, okay? ומותרן *U-motan*, and the difference between those is the value
of the oranges on the trees. And that's not considered קרקע karka
*karka*, that's considered פירות peiros, *peirot*, because the oranges on the trees
are not going to be are not going to be lasting and
generating income. They're going to be picked and consumed, right? So that's
not considered קרקע karka. *karka*, that value. So therefore, ילקח בהן קרקע
karka והוא אוכל פירות peiros. *Yilkach bahen karka ve-hu ochel peirot*. You
have to use that money that... you know, then you're going to
pick the oranges, sell the oranges or whatever. So basically, let's say
the oranges when they were on the tree were worth a thousand
dollars. After they're picked and harvested and sold at the market, they're
however delivered to the market, they're worth two
thousand dollars. So... what if it's five hundred? So not... okay. On
the tree and fifteen hundred once they're picked and harvested, okay. So
the extra thousand increase let's ignore the amount of what you had
to pay in order to pick them the extra thousand increase is
the פירות peiros. *peirot* that were generated from this קרקע karka. *karka*
that she inherited. That goes straight to the husband's pocket. Was that
clear? Because she got this land with oranges on the trees and
the oranges were picked. So now, and they increased in value
a thousand dollars, so
the market fifteen hundred... Whatever, yeah, that's whatever. You get a hired
picker to pick them the whole thing. So now their picked oranges
are worth fifteen hundred. That increase of a thousand dollars, that goes
straight פירות peirot *peirot* off of this land and goes into his
pocket. But how about the five hundred dollars? That was a thousand
of the fifteen hundred you just sold them for. But how about
that first five hundred? Was that considered פירות peirot *peirot* that were
generated by the field and goes straight into his pocket, or was
that there since it was included in everything that she just, like,
inherited? Right, she just inherited the whole land with the oranges on
the tree. So that five hundred dollars is part of the קרקע
karka, *karka*. So that five hundred dollars, she takes, she buys land
with it, and that land continues is in her title and continues
to generate income for the husband. Is that clear? No, not at
all clear. Because from that point on, all the פירות peirot *peirot*
go straight into his pocket. Wait, wait, it's five hundred dollars on
the
tree, it's fifteen hundred dollars after they're picked. Yeah. Okay, so you
can't double-dip with that five hundred.
You're not double-dipping. She inherits this plot of land with... right? Okay,
and it's got these oranges. Okay, now you have the boxes of
the oranges, okay, whatever, apples. Okay, fine, whatever. Okay, this sells for
1500 dollars. On the trees, the increased value was 500, okay? So
now you went ahead and you picked them and you sold them
into the market. So a thousand dollars now, this is since she
inherited this, okay, this thing since she inherited it has increased by
a thousand dollars because you've got all these pickers to hire. That
thousand dollars is פירות, peirot. that goes straight to the husband. Right.
Okay, what do you do with the extra 500 dollars that you
got? So the most logical thing to say is that was part
of what she inherited, that's part of the גוף guf of her
title to... she has title to all of the value of this.
So the 500 dollars that you got, she's going to buy more
קרקע, karka, retain title to it, and that will continue to generate
income for the husband, as opposed to saying, no, that was פירות,
peirot. it's פירות peirot. or whatever, that's considered פירות peirot, from the
קרקע karka. and that 500 dollars goes straight into his pocket. There
go the two paths go right there.
500 dollars. Let's suppose this is an orchard and there's a harvest.
Yes. And the fruit's worth nothing on the tree until it goes
to market.
That's the opinion that says that it's all considered to be פירות
peirot, and the husband gets the whole 1500. It's because of the
opinion when she inherited it... it was worth nothing. Wait, wait. So
that's one opinion. But the other opinion is no, fruit on the
trees are worth a lot more than
no fruit on the trees. When she inherited it it was 1000
dollars, but now it's
1500 dollars.
No, but if it was... if she inherited it with the... with
the field with the trees at 1500. Yeah. Then three months later
there's fruit on the trees. Okay. So what's
the... what's that extra... the
extra 500 dollars?
And that's the debate between the תנא קמא Tanna Kama and Rabbi
Shimon in the משנה. Alright, I know you love talking about it.
Okay, so the משנה says this: אלו הן הנכסים שנכנסים ויוצאים עמה.
Eilu hein hanichasim shenichnasim veyotzim imah. פירות המחוברים לקרקע, peirot hamichubarim lakarka,
פירות המחוברים לקרקע, Peirot hamichubarim lakarka, ומותר, umotar, the difference, those 500
dollars that the fruit is worth on the trees, ילקח בהן קרקע
karka, והוא אוכל פירות. peirot? That's part of what she inherited, that's
what she has title to. She retains that title to that value
of the פירות, peirot, so she's going to use that to buy
land and it'll generate more income but at least she'll retain the
title. והתלושין מן הקרקע שלו, Vahatlushin min hakarka shelo, and the stuff
that was on the... when she inherited it, that's considered basically
his. Meaning, when it gets picked, it'll all be his, and when
it gets picked,
those are just פירות. peirot So here, so if she's got it
picked, it'll all be his, 1500 dollars we saw before, all goes
into his pocket. Okay, this is considered to be now just קרקע
karka and trees, no more the פירות. peirot. When the פירות peirot,
are picked, they are the fruit that was produced by her field.
המחוברים לקרקע שלו. Hamichubarim lakarka shelo. Now what do you mean והתלושין
מן הקרקע שלו? vahatlushin min hakarka shelo? That means if she inherited
it after the bushels of fruit, right? Then more clearly, it's stuff
that she has title to and then that gets converted into קרקע.
Okay. וילקח בהן קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. Vyilakach bahen karka vehu ochel
peirot. Fine. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: מקום שיפה כוחה בכניסתה
הורע כוחה ביציאתה. makom sheyafeh kochah bichnisatah hura kochah biyitziasah. Where her
strength is stronger when she comes into the marriage, it's weaker when
she goes out. מקום שהורע כוחה בכניסתה יפה כוחה ביציאתה. Makom shehura
kochah bichnisatah yafeh kochah biyitziasah. The her strength is weaker when it
comes into the marriage, it's stronger when it goes out. What does
this
mean? כיצד? Keitzad? פירות peirot המחוברים לקרקע, so the fruit that was
attached to the land, the apples on the tree, בכניסתה שלו. bichnisatah
shelo.
So if that's the way it was when they got married, then
that is going to be his. Okay, which is like the position
of the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, that's considered, he gets it all because
it's going to be... like... now it's considered part of קרקע and
when it gets picked it's all his. Okay, this is like the
חכמים. Chachamim. בכניסתה שלו ביציאתה. Bichnisatah shelo biyitziasah.
Now let's say they get divorced
and her her field now has, doesn't matter what state it was
when they were married, but her orchard now has apples on the
trees when they get divorced. So who gets the... who gets that?
She takes back, she retains title on this stuff, so she gets
the trees on the... the apples on the trees. It's the same
logic. The apples on the trees are considered part of the קרקע.
So whereas when she comes in, they're part of the קרקע, they
get picked, they're פירות peirot. of קרקע, he gets it all. If
she gets divorced and she has apples on the trees, she doesn't
have to pay for those apples, that's part of her קרקע. Okay,
so that's that's hers.
והתלושין מן הקרקע, Vahatlushin min hakarka, if she comes into the marriage
and she's got bushels of apples, so בכניסתה שלה, bichnisatah shelah, that
when she comes in, that's considered to be, you know, stuff she
has title to and that's hers, that's not פירות, peirot that's hers.
וביציאתה שלו, Uvitziasah shelo, but when she goes out, if they've been
picked, who do they belong by now? The fruit that were picked
during the marriage?
Him. They belong by him. Yeah, but they were picked during the
marriage. As soon as they're picked, they're his. And then they got
divorced a day later. So he's smart, he gets the divorce just
to have his own? Wait, they got divorced and then they would
collect this? No, no, that was the first case. But they were
divorced when it was still on the tree. But they divorced after
they collected. Then what, exactly? Okay, so basically but it's the same
logic, okay, fine. Alright,
segment. Moving on. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, all that
was very interesting about making sure it gets converted into income-bearing, it's
something that's income-bearing that maintains the that the principal retains the value,
but of course the question's going to be like and it sounds
like basically that he can sort of insist on that, okay, since
he's entitled to the פירות, peirot? but presumably why you have to
say that, that he can insist on I need, I want you
to buy something that's income-bearing or whatever. But more so, there's a
debate about what to invest the money in. He wants to invest
the money in, you know, fields. He wants to invest the money
in rental property, right? Or into a, you know, into a Madoff's
account because he heard he gets 12% every single year, right? So
who gets to make those decisions about what about how you know
what to invest the money into, what's converted into. So let's take
a look. גמרא Gemara says like this: פשיטא Peshita is
obvious, ארעא ובתי, ar'a u-vatei, ארעא. ar'a. If there's a question whether
to buy land or whether to buy rental property, ארעא ar'a means
fields, agriculture property. ארעא, ar'a, you buy agriculture property. Now why? Okay,
so why would that be the case? So רשי Rashi basically says
because the rental property has a more certain income and a more
secure principal. Of course what's the גמרא Gemara. doing, just giving you
financial advice and saying you have to do the better investment? So
תוספות Tosafos word would do it in a more interesting way. He
says
that the field maintains the value, okay, but do not generate as
much income. The houses require more, lose their value, if people live
in a house and constantly have to do repairs, you have to
sink more money into it, okay, but will generate more income. So
guess which one the husband wants, guess which one the wife wants?
The wife wants the one with a more secure principal, and the
husband wants the one with the higher income. So the הלכה halacha
is we protect the interests of the wife. ארעא, ar'a, she's entitled
to insist on the one that has the more secure principal, okay?
What if they happen to reverse it? That'd be an interesting question.
Then presumably you would go by the husband, but because what,
no what if the husband for whatever reason, he was more conservative-minded
and the wife was more of a risk-taker? So he wanted to
keep ארעא, ar'a, and she wanted to buy, you know, and she
wanted to do the higher income-generating one, right? So that would be
interesting, because is it just that you favor the wife because at
the end she's entitled to it? Or is it that you favor
her when she wants the thing that's going to protect her principal,
right? Because she's hoping it happens, the principal is her thing. Yeah
right, so that's, I mean these are really interesting questions, right? I
mean if she wants to take risk... Oh and that's where the
תוספות Tosafos word goes. רשי Rashi just says you do buy the
one that's the better investment, which isn't an interesting reading. תוספות Tosafos
says that you do the one, if she insists on the one
that more protects the principal, even if it's lower income-generating, you listen
to her. Okay, what if things don't line up that easy, that
clear, it's not clear? But we do also, there's one question which
is protecting principal, another question which is generating income at risk of
the principal, the other is a question about the amount of additional
income and investment that it would take. Like if you got a
field, you got to hire laborers and all these other types, and
תוספות Tosafos throws that in. Exactly, rental property means it's for permanent
use, it's super... I understand, but that's a factor too, right? Maybe
he wants the one that's, you know, that would require less investment,
because the investment's coming out of his pocket. And she wants the
one that's going to require more investment, right? Or if he buys
a field and he does more investment, then it'll improve the field
so if she gets divorced, she'll get a better field to come
away with. So there's like a lot of factors, who do you
listen to? Alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
So the גמרא doesn't spell out all of these חשבונות. cheshbonos. Anyway,
okay, but anyway again according to the תוספות Tosafos word the reading
is you go by the one that protects the principal if she
wants that one. Okay.
ארעא ובתי, ar'a u-vatei, ארעא. ar'a. בתי ודיקלי, batei u-diklei, בתי. batei.
Houses or palm trees? בתי, batei, you buy houses because again like
the תוספות Tosafos word, that's a more, that more protects the principal.
דיקלי ואילני, diklei u-ilanei, palm trees and other types of trees, דיקלי.
diklei. Palm trees,
the principal is palm
trees vs fruit trees?
Yeah, but you have the fruit tree, okay, and it produces פירות.
peirot Yeah, but which one is the principal more secure? They all
are cases in which you have a principal and it produces פירות.
peirot But the question is which one are you more protecting the
principal? It's like well, you want to invest in bonds? So okay,
you got a lower return, but you got a more secure principal.
You want to invest in the stock market? You're making more of
a risk on the principal, but maybe higher returns. Right? Okay. So
that's the question.
בתי ודיקלי, batei u-diklei, בתי batei is a more conservative investment and
דיקלי diklei is a more of a risk of the principal. I
don't know, let's not argue. בתי. batei. דיקלי ואילני, diklei u-ilanei, palm
trees and other types of trees, דיקלי. diklei. But palm trees are
ones that are more secure
principal. אילני Ilanei דגופני, Degufni, other trees and vines,
אילני Ilanei are the other types of trees. Okay fine, so they
go over the question, there's so many different potential factors, but again
Tosafot reads it that you favor the wife if she's insisting on
the one that has more of a secure
principal. ארזא דבייתא ופירא דחופרי. Arza de-veita u-feira de-chifrei. Now let's say
we've got this
place of wood to be cut down, so we've got a forest,
where it's basically not producing fruit, you know what you're getting out
of the forest? Timber. Okay. And we also have a pond or
a river that has fish. Okay. So here's the question: is the
timber of the forest פירות peiros or קרן? keren, Is the fish
of a pond פירות peiros or קרן? keren, Because it's like actually
like the pond itself doesn't generate fish, I mean yes fish can
generate more fish, but okay, so how do you consider
them? ארזא דבייתא ופירא דחופרי. Arza de-veita u-feira de-chifrei. אמרי לה פירות,
Amri lah peirot, some say you consider that to be fruit, ואמרי
לה קרן, ve-amri lah keren, some say you consider it to be
principal. Okay. And therefore the issue will be if the woman inherited
that forest with the trees, okay, so Tosafot asks: אמרי לה פירות
מיפנא דאבושי קצת העצים והדגים שבחפיפה הוא פירותן והעיקר הוא הקרן. amri
lah peirot mifna d'avushei ketzat ha-itzim ve-hadagim she-ba-chafifa hu peirotan ve-ha-ikar hu
ha-keren. So if it's פירות peiros it means you chop down the
trees and the husband gets all the value of the timber. So
that's if you consider it פירות. peiros ואמרי לה כולי האי הוא
קרן, Ve-amri lah kulei hai hu keren, הני עצים ודגים עיקרן מהקר,
hani itzim ve-dagim ikaran me-hakar, since they don't regenerate automatically, וכל הנמכר
מיד איהו קרן והקורא הוא פירות. ve-chol ha-nimkar miyad ihu keren ve-ha-kora
hu peirot. So he doesn't actually get the timber, that's all hers
as the principal. So when you sell the timber then that goes
into her pocket and then she has to buy more stuff with
it that will generate
פירות. peiros. But that's not considered
to have
פירות. peiros.
Like
that's all considered to be that you're cutting into the קרן, keren.
that's not considered to be the פירות, peiros, which is interesting. Okay.
Now the Mishnah says: כללא דמילתא, Klala de-milsa, the general rule is,
דגזעו מחליף de-giz'o machlif פירות, peiros. if basically the thing replenishes itself
then it's fruit, right, אין גזעו מחליף ein giz'o machlif קרן, keren,
it doesn't replenish itself, principal, and we're going to talk about later
what if it's like a mine and you extract the ore or
something like that, like that might be considered קרן. keren, Now, what
if she has an oil well? Okay? So all the oil that
comes from it, she owns that money according to this, and okay,
but then you use that money to buy something that would generate
income and then he gets the income that would be generated from
that, but she actually owns all that stuff because it's a non-replenishable
resource. Yeah, although it is interesting, you know, because a forest with
trees, it is replenishable, but I guess
it doesn't grow back so fast. Right, exactly. I mean
although it is interesting because what do you call it, like fish,
how much is the fish, like it's the next year's spawning season,
right? I don't know, anyway, okay, moving on. אמר
רבי אמי אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי ואמרי לה אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי Amar
Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi ve-amri lah amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi
הגונב ולד בהמה מילוג, ha-goneiv vlad behemah me-lokh, let's see if we
can push it for the next time. Somebody steals a child of
this, you know, the woman came in with a flock of sheep,
the sheep gave birth to a little baby lamb, and somebody saw
it, right, someone else doesn't want, someone steals it, משלם תשלומי כפל
לאשה, meshalam tashlumei khefel l'ishah,
you pay double to the woman, which basically says the woman owns
the lamb. Now why shouldn't the lamb be
פירות? peiros? So כמאן לא כרבנן ולא כחנניה. ke-man lo ke-Rabbanan ve-lo
ke-Chananyah. Well, it's not like the Rabbanan and Hananiah. דתניא: De-tanya: ולד
בהמה מילוג לבעל, vlad behemah me-lokh l'baal, the child of these animals
that she brings in that she's entitled to belongs to the husband,
it's פירות, peiros, ולד שפחה מילוג לאשה, vlad shifchah me-lokh l'ishah, but
the child of a female slave belongs to the woman, okay, we'll
see why. וחנניה בן עקביא אומר עשו ולד שפחה מילוג כולד בהמת
מילוג. Ve-Chananyah ben Akavia omer asu vlad shifchah me-lokh ke-vlad behemas me-lokh.
No, it's the case of the slave woman is just like the
case of the animal, it all belongs to the husband. So everyone
says at least the animal, the פירות peiros, are the husband, it's
considered פירות. peiros, So what's the explanation? It says no, אפילו תימא
דברי הכל, afilu teima divrei hakol, everybody could agree to this idea
of
כפל. kefel. פירות תיקנו ליה רבנן פירא דפירא לא תיקנו ליה רבנן.
Peirot tiktinu lei Rabbanan peira de-peira lo tiktinu lei Rabbanan. He gets
the פירות, peiros not the פירות peiros of the פירות. peiros What
are the פירות of the פירות? So כפל kefel is seen as
a פירא. peira. Okay, it's some type of an income that was
generated by the, so the husband gets the קרן, the guy steals
the lamb, the husband gets the קרן, he owns the lamb, but
he doesn't get the כפל, kefel, that was some income that was
generated by the lamb that's כפל kefel of כפל kefel and that
goes to the wife. So Tosafot makes two points. The first point
Tosafot makes is, first of all, this idea you don't get the
פירות of the פירות is only something like כפל kefel which is
not a sort of natural thing, it comes from the outside. If
this lamb grows up and then has more... of the lambs. For
his? I mean we're gonna see later when there's פירות of פירות
of פירות of פירות and on and on and on. Okay once
he owns the lamb, he owns all of the future generations of
the lamb. So it's only this weird thing that this כסף kesef
that wasn't a natural thing and it's bizarre. He owns the lamb
but he doesn't own the כסף kesef of the lamb? And תוספות
Tosfos points out another irony. He says like wait wait let's get
this straight. Somebody steals the lamb itself, the mother, the ewe, the
sheep itself that she came in with. Okay who gets the כפל?
kefel? The husband because the husband gets פירות. Somebody steals even though
she owns the lamb, she owns the sheep. The husband gets the
כפל kefel because that's פירות. She says okay, so somebody then goes
ahead and steals the lamb that the husband owns and he doesn't
get the כפל. kefel. She gets the כפל, kefel, right? It's completely
bizarre.
So this is very
very
bizarre. So basically means that once he owns the פירות, he owns
all future generations. Okay, but now let's check out this debate about
the שפחה. shifcha. בשלמא לחנניה היינו דאיכא בינייהו מיתה. Bishlama le-Chananya haynu
de-ika beinaihu misa. We understand why חנניה Chananya says that the husband
gets the the lamb and the baby because he's not concerned about
death of the mother. Let's see why that matters in a minute.
אלא רבנן אי חיישי למיתה, Ela rabanan ei chayshi le-misa, but the
rabbis if they are concerned about death, אפילו ולד בהמה נמי לא
afillu valad beheima nami lo
then the husband shouldn't get the lamb. Now what's the logic? Of
course he gets the lamb, it's the פירות. No, here's the logic.
How much is a flock of sheep or if you want, female
servants, how much is that like קרקע, like a protected principal and
all it does is generate פירות? Because you know people die and
sheep die. So it's not exactly the idea of like a principal
that just generates פירות, the principal will at one time give its
own way. Okay, you have to amortize it, whatever. So maybe if
you have that type of a principal, even though it's he should
be entitled to the פירות, remember you're trying to protect her principal.
So maybe what you do is when you have these פירות, you
actually don't just give them straight to him. What you do with
those פירות is you actually give them to her and that she
then will reinvest that money and then that continues to generate פירות
for him. So some of what comes out of the פירות is
used essentially to reinvest and to protect her core principal when the
principal is not you know can deteriorate in value, can die. Okay,
so that's the logic. And then it doesn't matter so he's got
these these sheep, he doesn't just get all the lambs because then
ten years from now like the יעקב Yaakov and לבן Lavan story,
all the original flock will die and she'll have no principal left.
So what you do is no, you actually reinvest, like in literal
terms you attach, you reinvest the dividends, okay? And so he was
going to get you know some of that if maybe you buy
קרקע with it because if you're constantly reinvesting then he gets nothing.
Okay, but anyway but you do do that but he does get
that in order to protect her principal. So if that's true about
the lambs,
okay, אי חיישי למיתה אפילו ולד בהמה נמי לא, ei chayshi le-misa
afillu valad beheima nami lo, if she's concerned about the lambs and
that's why the husband owns the and that's why she owns the
child of the female slave, then then he also should own or
she should own also the lambs. ואי לא חיישי למיתה, ve-ei lo
chayshi le-misa, if you're not concerned about death and that's why he
owns the lambs, אפילו ולד שפחה נמי, afillu valad shifcha nami, the
husband should also own the baby
slave. הגמרא Ha-Gemara says ולעולם חיישי למיתה. ve-le-olam chayshi le-misa. Okay, he
is concerned about death and therefore she should get what's produced here
to protect her principal. And then you know maybe he has to
buy
a lamb back but she should get this to protect her principal.
ושאני בהמה דאיכא עורות, ve-shani beheima de-ika oros,
but the reason that she does not get the כפל kefel of
the lambs, what? Because you know why? Because her principal isn't really
totally at risk. Even if the lambs die, she can still go
ahead and sell them for their for their skin. Of course that's
a very trivial amount that she's able to retain. Okay, but here
you get this idea about when is it considered that her principal
is to some degree at risk that she go ahead and we're
going to you know and then as a result of that, you
know she'll be able to reinvest some of what the income that
it produces. Okay, we'll just read one more line as I'm going
to have to finish tomorrow. אמר רב זביד משמיה דאבימי הלכה כחנניה,
Amar Rav Zevid mishmiya de-Abimi halacha ke-Chananya, we rule like חנניה. Chananya.
Okay
and
things are just going to have to end. I'm sorry but we'll
end with the thought that we will pick up tomorrow.